Guide to the Alfred Hulse Brooks Photographs and Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Alfred Hulse Brooks photographs and papers
1892-1955
1898-1924
WA Photos 444
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
6.17
(13 boxes)
Photographs and papers created and collected by Alfred Hulse Brooks and then probably maintained by Philip Sidney Smith, his successor as Geologist in Charge of the Division of Alaskan Mineral Resources of the United States Geological Survey. The collection provides visual documentation of the work of the United States Geological Survey in Alaska. Most of the photographs were made by Brooks and other employees of the agency. Some images document joint surveys made with the Geological Survey of Canada. The photographs depict mining operations, water and rail transportation, frontier communities, and Native American villages. Locations in Alaska well represented in the collection include Fairbanks, Juneau, Kennecott, Ketchikan, Skagway, Valdez, and Wrangell, as well as sites along the rivers, including the Copper River, Susitna River, and Tanana River. Numerous images throughout the collection also document sites in Canada, particularly in British Columbia. Photographs not created by the United States Geological Survey or its employees consist chiefly of images created by commercial photographers, corporate bodies, and government agencies in Alaska, collected principally by Brooks to supplement those created by him and his subordinates. Significant components include photographs related to the Cook Inlet Exploration Expedition under the command of Captain Edwin Forbes Glenn (1857-1926) in south-central Alaska in 1898; trips made by Robert Steed Dunn (1877-1955) in Alaska, 1900-1908; and the first successful ascent of the eastern peak of Mount Blackburn (later called Mount Kennedy) made by Dora Keen in May 1912.
Brooks, Alfred H. (Alfred Hulse), 1871-1924
Smith, Philip S. (Philip Sidney), 1877-1949
Geological Survey (U.S.)
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Vintage Photographs on the Arthur Corbitt Hoskins Memorial Fund, 2009.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Alfred Hulse Brooks (1871-1924)
Alfred Hulse Brooks, an American geologist, was born in Ann Arbor, Michigan. He was the son of Martha G. Brooks (born 1850) and Thomas Benton Brooks (1836-1900), a mining engineer and geologist. Brooks received his elementary and secondary education in Newburgh, New York. He studied engineering in the Polytechnik Instituts of Stuttgart (1889) and of Munich (1890), and graduated from Harvard University in 1894.
During his studies, Brooks worked as a junior member of topographical mapping parties of the United States Geological Survey in Vermont (1888) and northern Michigan (1889), and in a geological party investigating potential iron ore lands in northern Michigan (1891). Upon graduation from Harvard, he gained an appointment with the United States Geological Survey and engaged in topographic and geological work in the Appalachian Mountains and Michigan. In August 1897, he attended the VIIth International Geological Congress in Saint Petersburg, Russia, and studied for several months in Paris, France, at the Muséum national d'Histoire naturelle and Collège de France.
In March 1898, Brooks began working for the United States Geological Survey in Alaska. Between 1899 and 1911, he participated in six major expeditions that traversed Alaska to map its topography and geology. From 1903 until his death, he was Geologist in Charge of the Division of Alaskan Mineral Resources of the United States Geological Survey.
Brooks was a vice-chairman of the Alaska Railroad Commission (1911-1912), as well as president of the Geological Society of Washington (1911) and of the Washington Academy of Sciences (1921). In 1913, in recognition of his contributions in exploring and mapping Alaska, he received the Charles P. Daly Medal of the American Geographical Society and the Conrad Malte-Brun Medal of the Société de Géographie (Paris). In 1917-1919, he served as chief geologist of the American Expeditionary Force in France.
In 1903, Brooks married Mabel Whitman Baker Brooks (1876-1962). They had a daughter and son, Mary (born 1906) and Thomas Benton (born 1910).
Philip Sidney Smith (1871-1924)
Philip Sidney Smith (1877-1949) was born in Medford, Massachusetts. He earned three degrees in geology from Harvard (A. B., 1899; A.M., 1900, and Ph.D., 1904, where he taught geology from 1903 to 1906. In 1906, he began work with the United States Geological Survey in Alaska. In 1915, he became the Administrative Geologist of the Geological Survey and was later Acting Director. In 1925, he became Geologist in Charge of the Division of Alaskan Mineral Resources of the United States Geological Survey. Smith retired from government service in 1944.
Scope and Contents
Photographs and papers created and collected by Alfred Hulse Brooks and then probably maintained by Philip Sidney Smith, his successor as Geologist in Charge of the Division of Alaskan Mineral Resources of the United States Geological Survey. The collection provides visual documentation of the work of the United States Geological Survey in Alaska. Most of the photographs were made by Brooks and other employees of the agency. Some images document joint surveys made with the Geological Survey of Canada. The photographs depict mining operations, water and rail transportation, frontier communities, and Native American villages. Locations in Alaska well represented in the collection include Fairbanks, Juneau, Kennecott, Ketchikan, Skagway, Valdez, and Wrangell, as well as sites along the rivers, including the Copper River, Susitna River, and Tanana River. Numerous images throughout the collection also document sites in Canada, particularly in British Columbia. Photographs not created by the United States Geological Survey or its employees consist chiefly of images created by commercial photographers, corporate bodies, and government agencies in Alaska, collected principally by Brooks to supplement those created by him and his subordinates. Significant components include photographs related to the Cook Inlet Exploration Expedition under the command of Captain Edwin Forbes Glenn (1857-1926) in south-central Alaska in 1898; trips made by Robert Steed Dunn (1877-1955) in Alaska, 1900-1908; and the first successful ascent of the eastern peak of Mount Blackburn (later called Mount Kennedy) made by Dora Keen in May 1912.
Most images depict locations in Alaska, except where noted. Each folder in the collection usually contains a single photographic print.
Arrangement
Organized into two series: Series I. Photographs and Other Work by Employees of the United States Geological Survey, 1898-1955. Series II. Photographs by Other Photographers, 1892-1936.
Geology -- Research -- Alaska -- Pictorial works; Geology -- Alaska -- Pictorial works; Indians of North America -- Pictorial works; Miners -- Alaska -- Pictorial works; Mines and mineral resources -- Alaska -- Pictorial works; Alaska -- Pictorial works; Alaska -- Discovery and exploration; British Columbia -- Pictorial works; Negatives (photographs); Photographic prints; Brooks, Alfred H. (Alfred Hulse), 1871-1924; Dunn, Robert, 1877-1955; Keen, Dora, 1871-; Smith, Philip S. (Philip Sidney), 1877-1949; Cook Inlet Exploring Expedition; Geological Survey (U.S.); Geological Survey of Canada -- Pictorial works
- Photographs and Other Work by Employees of the United States Geological Survey, 1898-1955; Series I; 4.42
  Arrangement
  Series I is organized into four subseries: Photographs Prepared for Publication and Other Work; Photographs by Identified Photographers; Photographs by Unidentified Photographers; and Photographic Negatives and Transparencies.
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of photographs created by or attributed to employees of the United States Geological Survey in Alaska that document the natural and built landscape in Alaska, as well as extractive industries, such as mining and fisheries.
  - Photographs Prepared for Publication and Other Work, 1900-1955
    Consists chiefly of photographs prepared to illustrate works published by the United States Geological Survey. Consists of photographic prints mounted on board or in folders. Most prints have annotations related to their reproduction. Also includes examples of maps created for publication by Brooks.
    Organized chronologically by publication or planned publication.
    - Eldridge, George Homans. A Reconnaissance in the Sushitna [sic] Basin and Adjacent Territory, Alaska, in 1898, 1900 (Box 1, Folder 1-5)
      Formed part of United States Geological Survey, "Explorations in Alaska in 1898," Twentieth Annual Report, Part VII. (1900).
      Images include Mount McKinley, Mount Susitna, Susitna River Valley, and Indian Creek.
    - Purington, Chester Wells. List of possible illustrations for Methods and Costs of Gravel and Placer Mining in Alaska, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Wright, Frederick Eugene, attributed. Typewritten labels for mineral samples collected from Prince of Wales Island and the Unuk River, British Columbia, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Biographical/Historical note
      Frederick Eugene Wright (1877-1953) was an American optician and geophysicist.
    - Collier, Arthur J., Frank Lee Hess, Philip Sidney Smith, and Alfred Hulse Brooks. The Gold Placers of Parts of Seward Peninsula, Alaska, Including the Nome, Council, Kougarok, Port Clarence, and Goodhope Precincts (Bulletin No. 328), 1908 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Photograph by Albert Barnes Kinne of Chauik Mountain from across Ophir Creek in 1903.
    - Covert, Clermont Calvert, and Clarence Eugene Ellsworth. Water Supply Investigations in the Yukon-Tanana Region, Alaska, 1907 and 1908, Fairbanks, Circle, and Rampart Districts (Water Supply Paper No. 228), 1909 (Box 1, Folder 9-10)
      Images include hydraulic mining on Eagle Creek, Hoosier Creek, and Little Minook Creek, and Thanksgiving Creek.
    - Porter, Elmer A., Placer Mining in the Fortymile and Seventymile River Districts, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 11-15)
      Formed part of Alfred Hulse Brooks et al., Mineral Resources of Alaska: Report on Progress of Investigations in 1911 (Bulletin No. 520)
      Images include hydraulic mining on Jack Wade Creek, the Mosquito Fork of the Fortymile River, and Crooked Creek.
    - Henshaw, Fred Forbes, Glenn Lane Parker, Philip Sidney Smith, and Alfred Hulse Brooks. Surface Water Supply of Seward Peninsula, Alaska (Water Supply Paper No. 314), 1913 (Box 1, Folder 16-20)
      Images include men using a large sluice box, also known as a "long tom," near Nome, and views of mining operations on Glacier Creek and Ophir Creek.
    - Prindle, Louis Marcus, Philip S. Smith, and Frank James Katz. A Geologic Reconnaissance of the Fairbanks Quadrangle, Alaska (Bulletin No. 525), 1913 (Box 1, Folder 21)
      Line drawing illustration of a head frame for a bucket hoist.
    - Ellsworth, Clarence Eugene, and Royal William Davenport. Surface Water Supply of the Yukon-Tanana Region, Alaska (Water Supply Paper No. 342), 1915 (Box 1, Folder 22-26)
      Images include Fortymile River, Little Minook Creek, Mastodon Creek, Quail Creek, Seventymile River, Troublesome Creek, and Wolverine Mountain.
    - Ellsworth, Clarence Eugene, and Royal William Davenport. A Water-Power Reconnaissance in South-Central Alaska (Water Supply Paper No. 372), 1915 (Box 1, Folder 27)
      View of Port Valdez, looking north.
    - Bagley, James Warren. Photographs that accompanied a presumably unpublished manuscript about diorite deposits in the vicinity of Sheep Creek and Kashwitna River, circa 1920 (Box 1, Folder 28-34)
    - Brooks, Alfred Hulse. Maps of Alaska, 1924 (Box 13, Folder 35-43)
      Distribution maps include navigable waters and railroads; copper deposits and producing areas; coal and petroleum; gold bearing areas and producing districts; vegetation; and arable land. Other maps outline physiographic provinces and mean annual temperatures and precipitation.
    - Smith, Philip Sidney, and Gerald Arthur FitzGerald. Geologic Reconnaissance Map of Northwestern Alaska, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Waring, Gerald A. Geology of the Anthracite Ridge Coal District, Alaska (Bulletin No. 861), 1936 (Box 1, Folder 45-53)
      Images include Anthracite Ridge, Chugach Mountains, Chikootna Creek, Purinton Creek, Kutzkatna Creek, Muddy Creek, and of a diamond core drill in operation.
    - List of illustrations to accompany a manuscript, probably by Gerald Arthur FitzGerald, Some Misconceptions Concerning Alaska for the Military Engineer, circa 1940 (Box 1, Folder 54)
    - Photographs that accompanied a report about the Whalen Mine, circa 1940 (Box 1, Folder 55)
    - Correspondence between Harvey Charles Orton of Chicago, Illinois, and Philip Sidney Smith, 1943 May 15-June 7 (Box 1, Folder 56)
      Letters about photographs that illustrate petroleum drilling operations in Controller Bay and near the Nichawak River.
    - Cady, Wallace Martin, et al. The Central Kuskokwim Region, Alaska; An Account of its Geography, Geology, Geomorphology, and Mineral Resources (Professional Paper No. 268), 1955 (Box 1, Folder 57-58)
      Images of the Kuskokwim River and Barometer Mountain made in June-August 1941.
  - Photographs by Identified Photographers, 1898-1942
    Photographs created by employees of the United States Geological Survey in Alaska. The majority of photographs are probably contact prints from negatives, as well as a small quantity of enlarged photographic prints or mounted contact prints. Photographs by James Madison Hill are accompanied by their corresponding original negatives. Some of the mounted prints were likely prepared for publication.
    Organized by photographer and therein by the numbering schemes the employees applied to them, followed by larger photographic prints or mounted prints with the same organization. They are followed by photographs by unidentified creators.
    - Brooks, Alfred Hulse, 1898-circa 1910 (Box 2, Folder 59-179)
      Views of Bluff, Chilkoot Trail, Chilkoot Pass, Chisana River, Copper River, Douglas Island, Eagle, Gastineau Channel, Holy Cross, Juneau, Ketchikan, Nome, Skagway, Skwentna, St. Michael, Susitna River, Sweetcake Creek, Tanana River, Tortella (which became Nenana), Treadwell Mine, Tyonek, White River, and Wrangell. Images also includes informal portraits of Brooks and other topographers, including William John Peters (1863-1942), as well as survey and mining camps; moose and caribou trophies; steamboats; and Native American communities, including totem poles and houses.
      A group of images also documents a trip by Brooks to Ireland, Scotland, and Switzerland in June-July 1906.
      - Trip to Ireland, Scotland, and Switzerland, 1906 June-July (Box 2, Folder 180-202)
        Views from the steamship Oceanic of the coast of Ireland; sites in Scotland, including the Caledonian Canal, a bridge at Inverness, Abbotsford House, and Melrose Abbey, as well as Lochs Katrine and Lomand; and views of the Bernese Alps, Switzerland, including a glacier on Eiger, as well as views of Grindelwald and Bern.
    - Cady, Wallace Martin, 1941-1943 (Box 3, Folder 203-206)
      Views of mining operations in the vicinity of Kuskokwim River, including Barometer Mine and Red Devil Mine.
    - Capps, Stephen Reid, 1910-circa 1920 (Box 3, Folder 207-213)
      Views include hydraulic mining in the Yentna Cache-Creek Mining District and a pack train crossing the Russell Glacier.
    - Chapin, Theodore Sheffield, circa 1910 (Box 3, Folder 214-219)
      Includes views of along the Copper River and Northwestern Railway.
    - Coats, Robert Roy, circa 1940 (Box 3, Folder 220-222)
      Images of hydraulic mining.
    - Collier, Arthur James, circa 1900-circa 1910 (Box 3, Folder 223-233)
      Images of mining operations, probably in the vicnity of Manley Hot Springs, as well as steam boats and canoes.
    - Eakin, Henry Miner, circa 1912 (Box 3, Folder 234-235)
      Includes a view of Juneau from Mount Logan.
    - Ellsworth, Clarence Eugene, circa 1910-circa 1912 (Box 3, Folder 236-239)
      Includes views of the Copper River and Northwestern Railway, the Alaska Railroad, and the Treadwell Mine.
    - Gilbert, Grove Karl, 1899 (Box 3, Folder 240-242)
      Includes a views of Yakutat and the Gastineau Channel, and an image of the mail steamer Dora.
    - Grant, Ulysses Sherman, 1908-circa 1910 (Box 3, Folder 243-244)
      Includes a view of the dock and ore bunkers of the Beatson-Bonanza Mine on La Touche Island.
    - Harrington, George Leavitt, 1916 (Box 3, Folder 245-247)
      Includes views of Faith Creek and from Mount Okumiak.
    - Hess, Frank Lee, circa 1908 (Box 3, Folder 248-250)
      Images includes steamboats, including the stern wheel steamboat Sarah.
    - Johnson, Bertrand Leroy, circa 1909-1911 (Box 3, Folder 251-260)
      Includes images of hydraulic mining and views of the Ellamar Copper Mine and an informal portrait of Alfred Hulse Brooks.
    - Katz, Frank James, circa 1904 (Box 3, Folder 261-262)
      Views consisting Tanalian Falls and a sailboat on Iliamna Lake.
    - Kindle, Edward Martin, circa 1910 (Box 3, Folder 263-264)
      Includes an informal portrait of a Native American family.
    - Knopf, Adolph, circa 1908 (Box 3, Folder 265)
      View of a mining operation from a distance.
    - Leffingwell, Ernest de Koven, 1906-1908 (Box 3, Folder 266-267)
      Images of Native Americans created during the Anglo-American Polar Expedition at Barrow, including a meal of Snow Goose eggs and skinning Dall Sheep.
    - Maddren, Alfred Geddes, 1909-1911 (Box 3, Folder 268-270)
      Views of a freight scow on the Upper Koyukuk River and of the Nolan Creek Valley.
    - Martin, George Curtis, circa 1910 (Box 3, Folder 271-276)
      Images of waterfronts, a steamboat, and pack train.
    - Mendenhall, Walter Curran, 1899-1901 (Box 3, Folder 277-284)
      Views of mining operations and exploration in the vicinity of the Dall River; views of Lake Laberge and Dawson City in the Yukon, Canada; and the mail steamer Dora at Hunter Bay.
    - Mertie, John Beaver, circa 1920 (Box 3, Folder 285)
      View of a man with a pack train of horses.
    - Moffit, Fred Howard, circa 1910 (Box 3, Folder 286-288)
      Includes views of men and packhorses along the Kenai River and of the Kennecott Mines.
    - Paige, Sidney, 1903-circa 1910 (Box 3, Folder 289-315)
      Includes views of mining operations in and around Eagle, Nome, and Ophir, as well as views of Skagway and of the White Pass Hotel Station. Also includes an informal portrait of a Native American with a spear.
    - Prindle, Louis Marcus, circa 1903-1910 (Box 3, Folder 316-332)
      Views of mining operations in the vicinity of Fairbanks, including Goldstream Creek and Mastoon Creek, as well as views of Quail Creek and Fortymile Creek.
    - Purington, Chester Wells, circa 1905 (Box 3, Folder 333-334)
      Images of mining operations on Pedro Creek and Ophir Creek and used to illustrate an article in Mining Magazine.
    - Reed, John Calvin, circa 1940 (Box 3, Folder 335)
      View from a distance of a mine on a waterfront.
    - Sargent, Rufus Harvey, circa 1925 (Box 3, Folder 336)
      Image of an Eskimo Umiak in the Bering Sea.
    - Schrader, Frank Charles, circa 1898-circa 1910 (Box 3, Folder 337-341)
      Views including the McPherson Fox Ranch on Naked Island, a mesa in the vicnity of the Koyukuk River and sluicing on Myrtle Creek.
    - Smith, Philip Sidney, circa 1905-1927 (Box 3, Folder 342-354)
      Views include steamboats among ice floes in the Bering Sea; an aerial view of a dredger; and mining operations at Willow Creek and Ophir Creek. Other images includes a man dismembering a whale at the Akutan whaling station and a group of gold nuggets.
    - Smith, Walter R., 1925 (Box 3, Folder 355)
      Dogs hauling a boat partly loaded over tundra in the Etivluk-Aniuk Pass.
    - Stone, Ralph Walter, circa 1904 (Box 3, Folder 356-357)
      Consists of views of ships, including freight steamboat Santa Clara and towing tugs Perry and Uncle Sam at Kayak
    - Townsend, Harry H., 1926 September (Box 3, Folder 358)
      View of a rock outcrop at the Stampede antimony mine at Stampede Creek
    - Wallace, Robert Earl, 1942 September (Box 3, Folder 359)
      View of the sternwheeler steamboat Wallace Langley.
    - Wright, Charles Will, 1905-1906 (Box 3, Folder 360-361)
      Consists of a view east from Mount Brown and a view of the United States Revenue Cutter Rush.
    - Enlargements and Mounted Photographic Prints
      - Brooks, Alfred Hulse, 1898 April-circa 1900 (Box 4, Folder 362-373)
        Includes images related to joint surveying expeditions by the United States Geological Survey and Geological Survey of Canada of Alaska and the British Northwest Territories at Marsh Lake, Yukon. Other images in Canada include Miles Canyon and the Yukon River, Yukon, and Bennett, British Columbia, as well as Chilkat Pass, between British Columbia and Alaska. Images in Alaska include views of the Bluff, Kelhini River, Pyramid Harbor, and Wrangell.
      - Capps, Stephen Reid, circa 1920 (Box 4, Folder 374)
        View of Iron Creek into the valley of a north flowing tributary.
      - Hill, James Madison, 1931 (Box 4, Folder 375-405)
        Images document several mining operations including Crites and Feldmann Mine, Elms Gold Mining Company, Eva Creek Mining Company, Fairbanks Exploration Company, Road Metal Quarry, Saint Paul Mill, and Zimmerman Hydraulic Mine. Locations of operations include Bedrock Creek, Chatnika River, Cleary Creek, Eva Creek, Ferry, Goldstream, Happy Creek, Moose Pup (a tributary of Fairbanks Creek), Saint Patrick Creek, Sourdough Creek, Twin Creek, and Wolf Creek.
      - Johnson, Bertrand Leroy, circa 1909 (Box 4, Folder 406)
        Image of hydraulic mining on Eagle Creek.
      - Mertie, John Beaver, circa 1940 (Box 4, Folder 407-408)
        Views of the Cassiterite Lode and surrounding country.
      - Paige, Sidney, 1904 (Box 4, Folder 409-410)
        Views of open cut mining on beach of Glacier Creek and an example of a derrick bucket.
      - Prindle, Louis Marcus, 1903-circa 1905 (Box 4, Folder 411-414)
        Images consist of a contorted schist near Mosquito Fork with an accompanying description by Prindle, and views of mining operations, including a steam shovel Mammoth Creek and sluices on Mastodon Creek.
      - Schrader, Frank Charles, circa 1899 (Box 4, Folder 415)
        View of the waterfront and beach of Nome.
      - Smith, Philip Sidney, circa 1905 (Box 4, Folder 416)
        Images of hydraulic mining on Daniels Creek.
  - Photographs by Unidentified Photographers
    Organized by location, including the lines of two Alaskan railroads, followed by subjects, then portraits of identified individuals and group portraits, and then the same organization applied to enlargements and mounted photographic prints.
    - Locations
      - Akutan, circa 1920 (Box 5, Folder 417-420)
        Images of processing a fin whale and removing its blubber
      - Alaska Railroad, circa 1915 (Box 5, Folder 421)
      - Anaconda Creek, circa 1910 (Box 5, Folder 422)
      - Anvik, circa 1910 (Box 5, Folder 423)
      - Barrow, circa 1910-1924 (Box 5, Folder 424-426)
        Images consist of an Iñupiat celebration and children playing
      - Broad Pass and a surveyor using a plane table, circa 1915 (Box 5, Folder 427)
      - Bull River, circa 1910 (Box 5, Folder 428-430)
      - Cantwell River, circa 1910-1923 (Box 5, Folder 431-434)
      - Chena, circa 1910 (Box 5, Folder 435)
      - Chulitna River, circa 1910 (Box 5, Folder 436-443)
      - Cordova, circa 1915 (Box 5, Folder 444-452)
      - Council City and Solomon River Railroad, 1903-1906 (Box 5, Folder 453)